A Guide to the Papers of Julian Bond, 1897-2006
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Julian Bond 1897-2006
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
13347
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
This collection is currently closed for research. Please contact Small Special Collections Library with any questions.
Series X is restricted until further notice.
Acquisition Information
These papers were placed at the University of Virginia on deposit by Julian Bond on June 25, 2005. They were purchased from Julian Bond by the University of Virginia Library in March 2007.
Biographical/Historical Information
Julian Bond was born in Nashville, Tennessee on January 14, 1940, to educator, Dr. Horace Mann Bond and his wife, librarian Julia Washington Bond, who had traveled there from central Georgia to have her child. In 1940, Dr. Bond was president of Fort Valley State College, a black institution in central Georgia. Julian Bond attended primary school at Lincoln University, Pennsylvania, where his father served as President, from 1945 until 1957, when Dr. Bond became dean of the School of Education at Atlanta University. His paternal grandparents were James Bond (1863-1929) born in Lawrenceburg, Kentucky, and Jane Alice Browne (1865-1938), born in Prince George County, Maryland.
He graduated in June 1957 from the George School, a co-educational Quaker preparatory school located in Bucks County, Pennsylvania and entered Morehouse College in Atlanta in the fall. While in Atlanta, Bond founded the Committee on Appeal for Human Rights (COAHR), the Atlanta University Center student organization that coordinated student protests against segregation in Atlanta for three years. In the summer of 1960, he also joined the staff of a new Atlanta weekly newspaper, The Atlanta Inquirer as a reporter and feature writer.
In January 1961, Julian Bond left Morehouse to become the Communications and Publicity Director for the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC), which was organized in 1960 at a conference of sit-in students on the campus of Atlanta University. He held that position until September 1966, traveling to Georgia, Alabama, Mississippi, and Arkansas to help with civil rights drives and voter registration campaigns.
He served in Georgia's House of Representatives, Atlanta's 111th District, from 1966-1975 and in the Georgia State Senate from 1975-1987. Bond was first elected to a seat created by reapportionment in the Georgia House of Representatives in 1965 but was prevented from taking office in January 1966 by members of the Georgia legislature objecting to his statements about the Vietnam War. After winning a second election in February 1966, a special House Committee again voted to bar him from office. Bond won a third election in November 1966, and in December the United States Supreme Court ruled that the Georgia House erred in not allowing him to take his seat in the legislature. On January 9, 1967, he was finally allowed to take the oath of office as a member of the Georgia House of Representative.
In 1968, Bond was Co-Chairman of the Georgia Loyal National Delegation to the Democratic Convention. The Loyalists were successful in unseating the hand-picked regulars and Bond was even nominated as the Democratic Party's first black candidate for Vice-President of the United States, but he was too young to serve. He also considered his own campaign for President in 1975-1976, taking preliminary steps to run for office.
More recently, he has taught popular Civil Rights history courses at American University (beginning in 1991) and the University of Virginia (beginning in 1990), and served as Chairman of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) from February 1998 until the present. Bond has served on many national boards and committees, including serving as the first president of the Southern Poverty Law Center in 1971 and continuing as President Emeritus; President of the Atlanta NAACP from 1978-1989; and President and Founder of the Southern Elections Fund (SEF), among many others.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the political and personal papers of Civil Rights activist, Georgia State Senator and Representative, and professor, Julian Bond (1940-), ca. 1897-2006, with copies of earlier material, consisting of ca. 47,000 items (134 Hollinger boxes, 1 Card File Box and 3 Oversize boxes, ca. 60 linear feet).
The first series, containing articles, speeches, and papers written and delivered by Julian Bond, is arranged by date if present or by an approximate date based on the subject or other internal evidence. When there is no title present on the document, the item is identified by its subject, place of delivery, or place of publication. Series one includes multiple drafts of various speeches; articles appearing eventually in print; statements and testimony before hearings, etc.; and tributes. The information in the box listing of the guide is sometimes more comprehensive than that recorded on the folder headings themselves.
The second series consists of various types of correspondence, often with the carbon of Julian Bond's response. Some years have only the carbon of Bond's response and not the original letter. These include arrangements for speaking engagements and political appearances, even though most events were arranged for him by the American Program Bureau (see separate correspondence in Boxes 61-65); correspondence with constituents concerning issues before the Georgia legislature; requests for his photograph and biographical sketch; correspondence with political representatives from other states concerning issues of common interest before the United States Congress; correspondence with members of organizations, such as the Southern Regional Council, asking for their advice or input concerning various ideas for publications or activities that he is considering; a few topical correspondence files, such as the issue of sterilization, South Africa, and the Angela Davis case; and Georgia politics.
Other types of correspondence include derogatory or racist "crank" mail; general requests including political memorabilia, research information, copies of speeches and articles by Bond, autographs, permissions to reprint poems, articles, etc., and requests for speaking appearances (which overlaps somewhat with the regular chronological correspondence files and the American Program Bureau files).
The third series includes papers and correspondence from members of various organizations concerned with voting rights, civil rights and minority issues. The largest groups of material include the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), National Urban League, the Southern Elections Fund, Southern Poverty Law Center, Southern Regional Council, Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC), and Voter Education Project.
Julian Bond's popularity as a political and civil rights speaker is evidenced by the fourth series which includes general invitations, his contracts and correspondence with the American Program Bureau, and his Political Associates files. The organization, Political Associates, is defined in a 1971 proposal as "an all-black Atlanta, Georgia based research group headed by Georgia State Representative Julian Bond" which is "initiating intensive investigations into the way black politicians - and black politics-operate."
The fifth series, Academic Papers, Speeches, and Writings, chiefly by other people, is arranged by type of material and then by author, and includes articles; books; class packets; a dissertation; interviews with Julian Bond by John Britton, William Chafe, Trevor L. Chandler, Marsha Darling, Jeffrey M. Elliot, Elizabeth Gritter, Megan Lisagor, Ulysses Prince, Plater Robinson, Thomas Rose and John Greenya, and Mr. Scavullo; papers by various scholars; poems; reports; speeches by others; student papers, many about Julian Bond; and theses.
The sixth series, political papers, is divided into a general group, which includes a lot of material about his own campaigns, Atlanta elections, endorsements and planning for black candidates, the Democratic National Committee and Conventions of 1968 and 1972, the Georgia and National Democratic parties, Georgia politics, and files on voting rights activities; and a second subseries, entirely concerned with his bid for the United States presidency in 1976.
Topical files comprise the seventh series, including both correspondence and papers about various topics of interest to Julian Bond or of use in his courses on the history of Civil Rights. Also included are files on the relationship of the Barnes Foundation and Lincoln University, once headed by Bond's father, Dr. Horace Mann Bond. Subseries B of the seventh series includes course evaluations, outlines, syllabi, research material, and lecture notes for courses taught by Julian Bond at The American University, Harvard University, and the University of Virginia.
Series eight, Family and Personal Papers, includes two subseries, the first concerning Julian Bond and the second, his extended family. His personal papers contain appointment books, activities and programs he attended, artifacts and memorabilia, honors and awards, correspondence with his family, financial files, and photographs, divided as much as possible into topics. The Bond Family subseries is chiefly concerned with Bond's parents, Horace Mann Bond and Julia Bond.
The ninth series, Publicity, includes columns written by Bond, his Georgia State Legislature newsletters, general news clippings, clippings about Julian Bond, and press releases and statements. The tenth series consists of restricted materials. The eleventh and last series consists of all audiovisual materials found in the collection, which are also catalogued individually and given a separate number.
Arrangement
Any original order has been preserved as much as possible. Files with no discernible order have been organized with similar types of material. These papers are arranged in eleven series, including:
Series I: Articles, Papers and Speeches by Julian Bond, arranged by date (Boxes 1-12)
Series II: Correspondence, including those labeled "Reading Files" (Boxes 12-36)
Series III: Organizations (Boxes 37-61)
Series IV: Invitations, Political Associates, and American Program Bureau Papers (Boxes 61-72)
Series V: Academic Papers, Speeches, and Writings, chiefly by Others, arranged by type of material and then by author (Boxes 73-80)
Series VI: Political Papers, with two subseries:
Subseries A: General (Boxes 80-93)
Subseries B: Campaign for President 1976 (Boxes 94-98)
Series VII: Topical Files, with two subseries:
Subseries A: General (Boxes 98-110)
Subseries B: Academic Course Evaluations and Lectures (Boxes 110-112)
Series VIII: Family and Personal Papers, including Photographs
Subseries A: Julian Bond (Boxes 113-122)
Subseries B: Bond Family Papers (123-126)
Series IX: Publicity including Newsletters, Press Releases, and News clippings (Boxes 127-132)
Series X: Restricted (Boxes 133-134)
Series XI: Audiovisual Materials
Contents List
- Series I: Articles and Speeches by Julian Bond
  - Article- Activism of the Late Mr. Allen in New South, 1964 March (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Article- Death of a Quiet Man: A Mississippi Postscript in Rights and Reviews, 1965 Winter (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Meet the Press NBC interview with Julian Bond, 1966 January 30 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Article on The Meaning and Measure of Black Power Symposium in Negro Digest,1966 November (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Article-The Story of Lewis Allen for The Sunday Ramparts, 1967 January 15-21 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Speech- Great Days Ahead concerning the plight of black farmers, [ca. 1967] (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Speech concerning the possibilities of politics for black citizens given at [Tulane University?], [ca. 1968 May?] (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Speech concerning the need to act with political unity, 1968 [June?] (Box-folder 1:8)
  - Speech of Julian Bond seconding the nomination of Senator Eugene McCarthy, 1968 [August] (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Speech at Bowling Green State University concerning young people in politics, 1968 November 22 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Speech concerning blacks and the election, 1968 [November?] (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Speech concerning the United States' move toward destruction, 1968 (Box-folder 1:12)
  - Symposium on the Contemporary South, Southern Perspective, Southern Educational Television Network, Special Edition from the University of Florida, [1968?] (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Speech concerning the constituents of Julian Bond and the recent election, ca. 1968 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Speech at the Hungry Club [Forum], Atlanta, Georgia, 1969 February 12 (Box-folder 1:15)
    Lamenting the changes brought about by the Nixon administration and predicting the election of a black mayor for Atlanta.
  - Speech at the Lexington Democratic Club Annual Dinner at the Plaza (Various Drafts), 1969 March 11 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Speech concerning health care for black people, 1969 June 25 (Box-folder 1:17)
  - Speech-Some Thoughts For Providing Assistance Backup For Elected Officials and Hopefuls at the Federal, State, and Local Levels, 1969 June 28 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - Speech- The Threat of Metropolitanism, 1969 June 28 (Box-folder 1:19)
  - Speech concerning the political and economic future of black people in Atlanta given before the Press Club, 1969 September 3 (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Speech before the Conference of Black Elected Officials, Washington, D.C. concerning the experiences of black people in the South in politics, 1969 September 14 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Speech concerning the conditions of black people, 1969 September (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Draft of an article for Playboy for their Holiday Anniversary Issue, Bring Us Together, 1969 September (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Speech on the crisis in race on college campuses, 1969 October 8 (Box-folder 1:24)
  - Address at the Dedication of W.E.B. Du Bois Memorial Park, Great Barrington, Massachusetts, 1969 October 18 (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Speech concerning the conditions of Southern blacks as compared with 1619, 1969 October (Box-folder 1:26)
  - Speech concerning the concept of "the System" and "the Establishment", 1969 October (Box-folder 1:27)
  - Speech on how politics in the South is changing, 1969 November 12 (Box-folder 1:28)
  - Speech on the failures of the Nixon Administration, 1969 November (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Address of Julian Bond to the Steering Committee Meeting of the National Urban Coalition, Washington, D.C., 1969 December 10 (Box-folder 2:2)
  - Speech before the Federation of Southern Cooperatives, 1969 (Box-folder 2:3)
  - Article excerpted from The Humanist concerning a new vision and better tomorrow, 1969 (Box-folder 2:4)
  - Speech concerning the American poor, [1969] (Box-folder 2:5)
  - Speech concerning the gap between black and white people, [1969] (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Scripts for the Rush Towards Freedom Television Series, 1970 January, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 2:7)
    Narrated by Julian Bond, with correspondence about the series, 1970-1972, and a negative of a Julian Bond photograph.
  - Speech- The Nature of the Crisis in Health Care Services in our Communities: as the Consumer Views the Problems, 1970 February 13 (Box-folder 2:8)
    Given before the National Health Forum, with a note to use again with speech to doctors in Atlanta on August 4th.
  - Background Paper on Medical Education and the Shortage of Physicians with a note to use again with speech to doctors in Atlanta on August 4th, 1970 March 31 (Box-folder 2:10)
  - Speech beginning with quote from W.E.B.Du Bois about the Problem of the 20th Century being the Color Line, 1970 March (Box-folder 2:11)
  - Introduction to the letters of George Jackson, 1970 June (Box-folder 2:12)
  - Speech concerning Black Voters and Officials delivered to the Voter Education Project, Inc., Capahosic, Virginia, 1970 July 24 (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Speech given at the Philadelphia Bar Association's Friday luncheon of the Bench-Bar Conference in Atlantic City, New Jersey on Black Americans and Marginal Citizenship, 1970 September (Box-folder 2:14)
  - Speech concerning the Future of Democracy and Black Needs given before the [Southern Christian Leadership Conference?], 1970 October 12 (Box-folder 2:15)
  - Working Outline for Julian Bond for a proposed speech in Atlanta, Georgia, written by Kelly Kidd, 1970 December 4 (Box-folder 2:16)
  - Speech at the University of Massachusetts concerning what the university should or will do, 1970 December (Box-folder 2:17)
  - Speech concerning the Black Experience in America, 1970 (Box-folder 2:18)
  - Speech concerning the United States as a Colonial Society, 1970 (Box-folder 2:19)
  - Speech concerning black Americans and the future of democracy, 1970 (Box-folder 2:20)
  - Speech concerning the threshold of a new era: environmental pollution and ecology, 1970 (Box-folder 2:21)
  - Speech about Politics and the Ways Policies Ignore Black Issues, [1970] (Box-folder 2:22)
  - Speech concerning the need for black unity at a congress, [1970] (Box-folder 2:23)
  - Speech concerning black Southerners and political parity, [1970] (Box-folder 2:24)
  - Speech concerning black people and economic stability, ca. 1970 (Box-folder 2:25)
  - Speech delivered to the ladies of Delta [Sigma Theta Sorority?], Atlanta, Georgia, ca. 1970 (Box-folder 2:26)
  - Speech concerning the Atlanta Inquirer and the black people of Atlanta, ca. 1970 (Box-folder 2:27)
  - Statement on National Priorities at the National Urban Coalition, 1971 January 18 (Box-folder 3:1)
  - Speech concerning opposition to the War in Southeast Asia, at the Angela Davis Rally, Miles College, Birmingham, Alabama, 1971 March 19 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Speech on the Kent State Murders, 1971 April (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Speech about the Practice of Politics and Black Voting Power, 1971 Spring (Box-folder 3:4)
  - Commencement Address to the University of Oregon, 1971 June 14 (Box-folder 3:5)
  - Statement about the Vietnam War, made via the telephone to Bill Shipp, 1971 June 22 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Draft Commencement Address to Howard University, 1971 June (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Speech concerning the Role of Young People in Government given to the Georgia Youth [?], 1971 July 26 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Speech concerning Youthful Activism and the Role They Play in the Struggle for Better Conditions, 1971 August 21 (Box-folder 3:9)
    Possibly given in San Juan, Puerto Rico.
  - Speech- Suburban Newspapers and the Black Community, 1971 August 30 (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Commencement Address at Wilberforce College, Ohio, 1971 August (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Proposal- Extensions on a Strategy for 1971-1972, 1971 September 2 (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Speech concerning Race and Economics as Problem of the 20th Century, 1971 September 14 (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Speech concerning what is wrong in the United States, before the [National Urban Coalition?], 1971 October (Box-folder 3:14)
  - Commencement Address at Morgan State University, Baltimore, Maryland, 1971 (Box-folder 3:15)
  - Commencement Address at Tuskegee University, Alabama, 1971 (Box-folder 3:16)
  - Speech concerning black people and the pressing issue of controlling their own lives, 1971 (Box-folder 3:17)
  - Speech concerning black and poor people: steps toward more participation in politics, 1971 (Box-folder 3:18)
  - Speech concerning black people and their way of life as "colonial subjects", 1971 (Box-folder 3:19)
  - Speech concerning Atlanta, Georgia and stability, [1971] (Box-folder 3:20)
  - Foreword to If They Come In the Morning: Voices of Resistance by Angela Y. Davis and Others, [ca. 1971] (Box-folder 3:21)
  - Speech concerning political action, black people in Florida and the Presidential Primary elections, at Sanford, Florida, 1972 January 4 (Box-folder 3:22)
  - Speech concerning the political status of education in the seventies, 1972 January 15 (Box-folder 3:23)
  - Speech about the roles of black students in addressing the multiplicity of afflictions affecting the black community, Morehouse College, Atlanta, Georgia, 1972 March 9 (Box-folder 3:24)
  - Introduction of Julian Bond by Elmo Ellis, before his speech to the Georgia Association of Broadcasters (not present), 1972 June 16 (Box-folder 3:25)
  - Speech about race and war in American life, 1972 June (Box-folder 3:26)
  - Speech about the black struggle and progress, National Urban League, St. Louis, Missouri, 1972 August 2 (Box-folder 3:27)
  - Speech concerning the trial of the RNA11 (Republic of New Africa 11), 1972 August 18 (Box-folder 3:28)
    Given at Jackson, Mississippi.
  - Speech for NSA on problems of race and class, 1972 August (Box-folder 3:29)
  - Speech about the upcoming presidential election, in [New Orleans, Louisiana?], 1972 October 5 (Box-folder 3:30)
  - Speeches making observations about the recent election and its effects upon black people, 1972 November (Box-folder 3:31)
  - Speech made at the Symposium on Civil Rights at the Lyndon Baines Johnson Library, University of Texas, 1972 December 12 (Box-folder 4:1)
    Austin, Texas, concerning the challenge of the seventies.
  - Speech made before the Hungry Club [Forum, Atlanta, Georgia] (Box-folder 4:2)
    Concerning his candidacy for one of the Democratic delegate seats from Georgia's 5th Congressional District for the March 11 Convention.
  - Speech from the Alabama Voter Education Project Tour concerning Young People and Politics, 1972 (Box-folder 4:3)
  - Speech concerning black people and traditional difficulties delivered to the Racial Harmony Council, 1972 (Box-folder 4:4)
  - Speech concerning black bankers and businesses, ca. 1972 (Box-folder 4:5)
  - Speech concerning challengers facing the American black people and possible solutions, [ca. 1972] (Box-folder 4:6)
  - Speech at Press Conference in Washington concerning the Vietnam War and the Bach Mai Hospital Emergency Relief Fund, 1973 January 2 (Box-folder 4:7)
  - Speech on the health of the United States education system, 1973 February 2 (Box-folder 4:8)
  - Speech at the National Urban League Meeting, Kansas City, Missouri, 1973 March 29 (Box-folder 4:9)
    Discussing the choices of the 1972 Elections.
  - Speech about the government's post-election attitude, 1973 May 8 (Box-folder 4:10)
  - Commencement Address at Federal City College, Washington, D.C., 1973 June 17 (Box-folder 4:11)
  - Commencement Address, 1973 June (Box-folder 4:12)
  - Testimony before the Commission on Delegate Selection and Party Structure, Atlanta, Georgia, 1973 July 20 (Box-folder 4:13)
  - Speech before the NCDH/Southern Regional Council Housing Conference, 1973 October 15 (Box-folder 4:14)
  - Speech before the National Association of Health Services Executives (NAHSE), 1973 October 19 (Box-folder 4:15)
    Health as a pressing issue for the black community.
  - Speech concerning the 1972 Presidential Election and what it meant for the voters, Chicago, Illinois, 1973 November 15 (Box-folder 4:16)
  - Speech concerning South Africa, 1973 (Box-folder 4:17)
  - Speech concerning the health of politics and their effect upon the nation following the resignation of President Richard Nixon, 1974 (Box-folder 4:18)
  - Article concerning accountability for black politicians for Black Collegian, 1974 (Box-folder 4:19)
  - Speech at the Martin Luther King, Jr. Center for Social Change Conference on the 1965 Voting Rights Act, 1975 January 13 (Box-folder 4:20)
  - Remarks prepared for the Southern Conference of Black Mayors, Grambling, Louisiana, 1975 March 7 (Box-folder 4:21)
  - Article- Self-Defense Against Rape: The Joanne Little Case in The Black Scholar, 1975 March (Box-folder 4:22)